<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Snarford in Lincolnshire at the funerals of Sir George Sanct-Paule, knight and baronet, December the 9. 1613 by Iohn Chadvvich ... ; together with a briefe and true relation of his vertuous life and holy death.</title>
            <author>Chadwich, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18351</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20212566</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20212566</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23814</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18351)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23814)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1707:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Snarford in Lincolnshire at the funerals of Sir George Sanct-Paule, knight and baronet, December the 9. 1613 by Iohn Chadvvich ... ; together with a briefe and true relation of his vertuous life and holy death.</title>
                  <author>Chadwich, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby for William Barret, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Three Pigeons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXXVII, 37 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23814:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23814:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT SNARFORD IN LIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COLNSHIRE AT THE FVNERALS of Sir GEORGE SANCT-PAVLE Knight and Baronet, December the 9. 1613. By IOHN CHADVVICH Doctor in DIVINITIE, AND ONE OF HIS Maieſties Chaplaines in Ordinarie.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH A BRIEFE and true RELATION of his vertuous life and holy death.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ESAY 57. v. 1.</bibl>
               <p>The righteous periſheth, and no man laieth it to heart: and mercifull men are taken away, none conſidering that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is taken away from the euill to come.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Woodcut printer's device of a mask with rings (McKerrow 379, lacking the letters A. H. below)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by William Stansby for William Barret, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Pauls Church-yard at the ſigne of the three Pigeons. 1614.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:23814:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23814:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT SNARFORD IN LINCOLNESHIRE AT THE Funerals of Sir GEORGE S<hi rend="sup">ct.</hi> PAVLE <hi>Knight and Baronet, the ninth of</hi> December 1613.</head>
            <head type="sub">THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 37. v. 37.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Marke the perfect man, and behold the iuſt: for the end of that man is peace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſaying is old and true, that thoſe things which are differing in their end, doe moſt oppoſitely diſagree. <hi>Diues</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> were of ſome likelihood whileſt they liued in the world: They were both made of one mould, informed with one ſpecifical forme, breathed in one aire, moued on one and the ſame earth: yet if we obſerue their conditions in their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:23814:3"/>ends, we ſhall finde as great oddes therein, as is betwixt felicitie and miſerie, death and life, heauen and hell; which are ſuch contraries as cannot bee reconciled nor made at one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> was much troubled to ſee the proſperous eſtate of the wicked, and the meane and troubleſome condition of the Lords children. But God who will not leaue his ſeruants in erronious conceipts, nor vnder the weariſome burden of fainting diſcontent, counſelleth his kingly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet not to be diſquieted though he ſee the workers of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie to flouriſh like a greene bay-tree, and the righteous to vndergoe much feare and trouble: for if hee marke but their ends, hee ſhall behold the wicked which draw out their ſword, and bend their bow to ſlay ſuch as bee of vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right conuerſation, that their ſword ſhall enter into their owne heart, and that like the graſſe they ſhall ſoone bee cut downe, and like the greene hearbe they ſhall wither away. But for the man that hath the law of his God in his heart, his ſteps ſhall not ſlide. For marke the perfect and vpright man: hee neither fadeth nor rotteth in his name, nor falleth nor faileth in his profeſſion and hope: for <hi>finis illius pax, his end and vpſhot is peace.</hi> Which point when <hi>Dauid</hi> had learned in Gods Sanctuary both by dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and obſeruation, he doth not keepe the knowledge thereof vnto himſelfe: but being eſtabliſhed in the truth, endeuoureth to confirme others in the ſame, by exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to obſerue the concluſion of good men, wherin they ſhall find ſuch matter of deſired comfort, as may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them to paſſe thorow all the difficulties which this preſent euill world can oppoſe againſt them.</p>
            <p>The words now read containe two parts. The firſt part ſheweth what be the properties of a good man. The
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:23814:3"/>ſecond part ſetteth downe what the end of a good man is; to wit peace.</p>
            <p>The properties, they are two, which I may call the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall parts of a Chriſtian: The former is perfection: the latter righteouſneſſe. For as man conſiſteth of two parts, the ſoule and body; ſo a good man is compoſed of two conſtituting properties. And as by the motions and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the bodie wee conclude, that it is informed with a liuing ſoule; ſo by the workes of righteouſneſſe we proue, that there is an inward perfection of holineſſe in the ſoule. And on the contrary ſide, as the ſoule is ſaid to bee flowen away when the body doth putrifie and corrupt; ſo wee may inferre that the ſoules inward beautie is gone, when the workes of iuſtice are not to be found. For ſaith the Prophet, When the Kings daughter is all glorious within, her garments without are of wrought gold; and therfore <hi>obſerua perfectum &amp; vide iuſtum,</hi> by the latter know the former as a true demonſtration thereof. The end of a good man thus deſcribed is peace. Which words <hi>I</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe are diuerſly vnderſtood: but I follow the laſt and beſt tranſlation, which is moſt agreeable to the originall. And thus hauing broken the words into their naturall parts, let vs ſee what nouriſhment wee may get by euery ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cantill: for ſure I am that there is not a crumme in any parcell of theſe words, but it containeth good meat for a Chriſtian ſoule to feed vpon.</p>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Obſerua perfectum.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith, that hee is perfect which was not made:
<note place="margin">Perfectus infectus.</note> and that is only true of God, who is that
<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.14.</note> 
                  <hi>I am</hi> that ſent <hi>Moyſes</hi> to <hi>Pharo,</hi> who is that
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1.</note> 
                  <hi>all-ſufficient</hi> that ſpake vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> that
<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Alpha and Omega,</hi> as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> calleth him. For as <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> ſaith, the perfection of God is to bee
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23814:4"/>of himſelfe and of no other,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and whatſoeuer tendeth to perfection is from him, as the Author and
<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iames</hi> 1.17.</note> giuer of it. Which being true, what then ſhould our Prophet meane to call any man perfect, of whoſe weakeneſſe and wants, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the report that the ſacred word doth make, which is both <hi>fidei &amp; morum norma,</hi> our daily experience doth let vs ſee, what lamentable defects are in all the ſeede of <hi>Adam.</hi> To ſoile this doubt, I anſwere, that there is a perfection in euery Chriſtian, which is that excellent forme, by which hee differeth from all the ſonnes of darkeneſſe, and out of which iſſueth ſtreames of a vertuous conuerſation. But this perfection is not in an abſolute freedome from ſinne, but in our vnion with Chriſt, in
<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.9.</note> whom doth dwell all the fullneſſe of the God-head bodily, and through whom all beleeuers are made partakers of the godly Nature, as Saint
<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, and out of whom they receiue grace for grace, as ſaith
<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.16.</note> S. <hi>Iohn.</hi> The greateſt perfection that man can attaine vnto, is, <hi>ſuae imperfection is cognitio,</hi> the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his wants: and therefore almightie God out of his infinite loue appointed a high Prieſt, euen <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> the Mediator of the new couenant, to make that perfect which by none other could be done. And therefore <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaith, that the perfection of a faithfull man is in <hi>cognitione Chriſti,</hi> whom truly to know is
<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.3.</note> eternall life, as our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour witneſſeth. But to come to the point.
<note place="margin">The two firſt are attained in this life. The laſt is partly attained in this life, and more fully in the world to come.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The perfection of a good man is either <hi>quoad</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>partes,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>veritatem,</hi> or</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>menſuram.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For the firſt; thoſe that are regenerate of water and the holy Ghoſt, as the Euangeliſt ſpeaketh, are by the Apoſtle called new borne Babes. Now as euery child ſo ſoone as he is borne is a perfect man, becauſe hee hath all the parts
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:23814:4"/>and lineaments of a man, howbeit he cannot ſhew any perfect action of a man: euen ſo thoſe that haue receiued the immortall ſeed of Gods truth, &amp;
<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.1.</note> hunger after the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere milke of Gods word, that they may grow thereby, are perfect in him who is the
<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10.</note> head of principalities and powers; perfect (I ſay) in reſpect of all the parts of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and true holineſſe, though they want ſuch excellent vſe thereof, as thoſe haue which are of riper yeares. And therefore the
<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.</note> Apoſtle calleth all beleeuers new creatures, both becauſe they are the workmanſhip of God, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe they haue the ſtampe of perfection vpon them, as the creatures which God did make, of which it is ſaid, <hi>he ſaw that they were good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hence appeareth the loue of God toward the weake ones in faith, that they are by him reſpected and accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of as perfect in their weakeſt infancie: much like a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing father, who though his child can performe no dutie of a man, yet doth he prouide meat to nouriſh him, clothes wherwith to couer him, means to preſerue and keepe him, yea a portion and an inheritance for him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as Gods tender loue appeareth hereby: ſo is mans happineſſe ſeene herein. Who though he be feeble and weake, to any thing that is good, either for the helping of himſelfe or others: yet is he cared for and eſteemed of, as though he were perfect in the performance of all duties of a ſonne-like obedience, and lacked nothing. For which cauſe you ſhall finde it often in the Scriptures, that when a good man conſidereth of his owne eſtate, he wanteth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter to complaine of, nor time of repentance. Yet when God looketh vpon
<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.47.</note> 
                  <hi>Nathaniel</hi> vnder the Figge-tree, vpon
<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Iob</hi> in the Eaſt countrey, vpon
<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Zacharie</hi> and <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth:</hi> he ſpeaketh of them as though they were void of all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:23814:5"/>defects and wants: for ſo cleere is the cryſtall glaſſe of his loue, through which he beholdeth his owne image in man, that howbeit S. <hi>Paule</hi> crieth out againſt his owne
<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</note> wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe, yet God aſſureth him, he being in Chriſt, that nothing can
<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> condemne him, nor ſeparate him from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happineſſe. And thus much for perfection <hi>Quoad partes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond is perfection <hi>Quoad veritatem.</hi> Whileſt man doth dwell in the houſe of clay, he hath faith, but with ſome doubting; hope, but with diſtruſt; loue, but with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlike. Yet becauſe his faith is true faith, God accounteth of him as compleat: for when the new man of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and
<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.22.</note> holineſſe of truth, is put on, as S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, there is the perfect obiect of Gods loue. And hence is that of S. <hi>Bern. Veritas liberat, ſaluat, lauat,</hi> It freeth a man from the intanglements of ſinne, it ſaueth him from running with hypocrites into the pollutions of vniuſt and diſſembling behauiours, yea it will waſh him from the ſwiniſh faſhion of thoſe who hold the veritie of God in vnrighteouſneſſe. The Scribes and Phariſees made a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſhew of vertue: but becauſe it wanted truth, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all their pompe came to the ground, and they had their
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.2.</note> reward. For their actions wanting the aduerbe, were to them like the Apples of Sodome, nothing but duſt and corruption.</p>
               <p>That word which <hi>Vatablus</hi> tranſlateth in my Text <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum,</hi> others haue conuerted <hi>veritatem,</hi> and ſome <hi>ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatem,</hi> and others <hi>integrum,</hi> and all to teach vs, that ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie and truth, in the profeſſion of holineſſe, giueth a man the name of perfection in Gods account. For he one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is a
<note n="b" place="margin">Homo quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</note> tetragoule and a foure-ſquared Chriſtian indeede, who doth <hi>toto pectore Deum colere,</hi> endeauor to honour and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23814:5"/>ſerue God with a ſound heart voide of hypocriſie: I know the beſt child of God findeth in himſelfe the law in
<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23.</note> his members, fighting againſt the law of his minde: is he ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſtitute of the truth of Gods grace? not ſo. Is wine no wine, becauſe there be many Lees in the ſame? Is wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter no water, becauſe it is cumbred &amp; troubled with mud? it were an vnreaſonable ſpeech to ſay ſo. And it is no leſſe diſagreeing from the truth, to thinke and ſay, that a man is no child of God, becauſe hee is troubled with the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances of ſinne. For the Lord beholding in whom there is true faith, hope, and brotherly charitie, which is <hi>vinculum perfectionis,</hi> as
<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, eſteemeth them for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, who are ſimply plaine and plainely ſimple without hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>The third perfection which I named to you in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, is perfection <hi>quoad menſuram:</hi> what? to a meaſure without defect or want, that is impoſſible to bee attained in this world. The perfection then which we muſt looke for in the third place is, to
<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13.</note> ſtriue forwards to that which is ſet before, and not to be wearie of well doing, till we come to a full meaſure of ſanctitie void of ſinne, which only is attained in the world to come. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Quot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quot perfecti ſumus ita ſentiamus.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vpon thoſe wordes thus ſpeaketh, <hi>Quotquot perfectè currimus, hoc ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quod nondum perfecti ſumus, &amp; illic perficiemur quò perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctè currimus.</hi> So many as runne perfectly vnderſtand thus much, that as yet they haue not attained perfection, but ſhall be made compleat there whereto they manfully run. Be you
<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 5.48.</note> perfect, like as your heauenly father is perfect, ſaith Chriſt, that is, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, ad perfectionem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendite,</hi> aime at perfection as the marke, whereupon you ſet your eies in all your Chriſtian attempts. For as the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23814:6"/>heauens and the earth are ſaid to be perfect, becauſe they moue and abide to that end whereunto God did appoint them, as <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſpeaketh: ſo hee that is borne not of the
<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.13.</note> will of the fleſh, but of the will of God, is ſaid to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, becauſe hee imploieth the parts of his bodie, and the powers of his ſoule, as
<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.</note> weapons of righteouſneſſe, till they come to the
<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.</note> fulneſſe of ioy; and neither ſtandeth ſtill, nor turneth backe, but goeth on vntill he haue finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his courſe, and haue the end of his faith, which is the
<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1.</note> ſaluation of his ſoule. In this world we ſee in part, wee know in part; and the greateſt meaſure to bee attained in compariſon of that which by hope is expected, is but like a drop of water to the Ocean, or a ſand by the ſea-ſhore to a mightie mountaine. But there will be a time when wee ſhall come vnto a perfect man,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13.</note> and vnto a meaſure of the fulneſſe of the age of Chriſt Ieſus: and when that that is perfect is come,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.10.</note> then that which is imperfect ſhall be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed. The concluſion then of this point is this, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit abſolute perfection is only in the author of all things, yet the true members of Chriſt haue receiued the firſt fruits of perfection, and are ſaid to bee perfect both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their integrall parts of ſanctitie, and in reſpect of the truth of holineſſe, and laſtly for that they enioy a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of perfection in the kingdome of grace, which ſhall be made compleat and abſolute wanting nothing in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory. For then our knowledge which was mixed with ignorance, ſhall be ſo excellent, that wee ſhall know as wee are knowne: then we ſhall ſee him, not in a glaſſe, but cleerely and without all defect: then our faith ſhall be turned into fruition, hope into hauing, loue ſhall abide without diſſimulation, and in a word wee ſhall be like him ſaith
<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> and ſee him as he is. Now as this excellent
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:23814:6"/>knowledge is afforded vnto vs out of theſe wordes: ſo the <hi>Pelagians</hi> haue gathered deadly poyſon from the ſame, to wit, That man may come to ſuch a height of perfection, as to bee deuoid of all ſinne in this world. Againſt whom S. <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth. The <hi>Valentinians,</hi> as <hi>Irene</hi> reporteth, haue taught the like, and that they haue ſeede of election in them: The <hi>Manichees</hi> thought that <hi>renati,</hi> ſuch as were regenerated, came to that perfection in this life, that they could not ſinne any more, <hi>ſi maxime velint,</hi> howbeit they did much deſire it. Againſt all theſe doe but apply the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of perfection before handled, and ſet downe, and wee ſhall ſee how vaine and idle, yea how blaſphemous theſe opinions are. But to leaue this to the wiſe diſcretion of the hearers, let vs ſee what may be ſaid againſt them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Scripture telleth vs, that we are all the ſeede of vncleaneneſſe:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.15.</note> and in reaſon no cleane thing can come from that which is polluted. Againe, the holieſt men that haue liued did complaine of their wants, and haue beene ſubiect to
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21.</note> death, which is the wage of ſinne, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh. And hath not our Sauiour taught all his Church continually to pray, <hi>forgiue vs our debts?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> which petition were needleſſe in caſe we had alreadie attained perfection.</p>
               <p>Adde to this, that perfection conſiſteth in a certaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, from which the beſt is ſo farre in this life, that as <hi>S. Bern.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nemo perfectus eſt qui perfectior eſſe non appetit.</hi> And if he hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt he hath no ſuperfluitie, either to lay by, or to afford others. Now if it be obiected that our Sauiour ſaith, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer drinketh of the water that he ſhall giue them, ſhall neuer be more a
<note n="q" place="margin">Which words are vnderſtood of the eſtate of a true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in this world.</note> thirſt; the anſwere is readie, that thirſt is not oppoſed to further deſire of the encreaſe of grace, and of the bleſſed Image of God, which is not fully reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:23814:7"/>till we poſſeſſe heauen,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but to a totall and finall falling from grace, which the childe of God ſhall bee free from, howbeit he finde many wants in himſelfe, and feele many oppoſitions againſt him whileſt hee is clothed with the houſe of clay. Not to proceed further in this point, the ſaying of <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> is good: <hi>Si qua fidelium hic eſſe poteſt perfectio, in eo conſiſtit, vt ſe imperfectos eſſe agnoſcant:</hi> If there be any perfection in this life, it is to know our wants, and to deſire a ſupply out of the rich treaſure of Gods goodneſſe. And where this is truly in any man, it will be ſeene by the practiſe of righteouſneſſe, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond propertie of a good man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Behold the iuſt.</head>
               <p>Where integritie and ſoundneſſe of faith is in the heart, it is like fire, which yeeldeth either heat, or flame, or both. Let <hi>Dauids</hi> heart be hot within him, words of grace will iſſue from him. For as the ſpirit of man is not idle, ſo the ſpirit of grace in man is euer working the thing that is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, either by ſuppreſſing euill, or acting good: wherein is the life of true iuſtice and righteouſneſſe. But to come more neerely to the point. This iuſt man which <hi>Dauid</hi> would haue vs to behold, muſt be conſidered in his foure dimenſions. The firſt whereof is his altitude, and that is in his abilitie to know the rule of righteouſneſſe, and to take the true height thereof. For what likelihood is there for a man to doe iuſtice, and to be ignorant of the bounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that hee muſt vſe in the practiſe thereof? Whence is that ſaying of <hi>S. Ambroſe; Male ſe rectum putat, qui regulam ſummae rectitudinis ignorat:</hi> He that vnderſtandeth not the rule of equitie, is very like to bee defectiue in all duties of righteouſneſſe. I grant that an ignorant man may doe right to another: but it is as the blinde man hitteth the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:23814:7"/>marke, or at the leaſt as he who ſaw men walking like trees: and I am ſure the former may as well miſſe as hit; ſo the latter doth notoriouſly miſtake the matter.</p>
               <p>The ſecond dimenſion is his latitude, which extendeth to the profiting of others as well as himſelfe. Of this our Prophet ſpeaketh in this Pſalme, when hee ſaith, that a good man is mercifull and lendeth: which act of charitie is for the good of borrowers more then of the lender, who oftentimes loſeth both his goods and the loue of his bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing friend. <hi>Iuſtus magis alijs quàm ſibi prodeſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Ambroſe:</hi> A iuſt man is more helpfull and gainfull to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers then himſelfe: and heerein hee reſembleth the eie in the body, which ſeeth all but it ſelfe; and the Lion-like Sunne in the firmament, which ſendeth out beames of glorious light to all but it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>The third point in the iuſt man is his longitude: and that is, to bee contented onely with that is a mans owne, and to ſtretch out the length of his deſire and endeuour to nothing that belongeth to another man, no not ſo much as in a wiſh. For as an ancient Father ſaith, <hi>Iuſtus nil alienum vendicat, ſed cuilibet dat quod ſuum eſt:</hi> The iuſt man clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth nothing but that is proper to himſelfe, and giueth to euery man that belongeth vnto him: to God his due, to <hi>Caeſar</hi> his owne, and that with a willing and a ready minde. And ſaluation is then come to <hi>Zaccheus</hi> houſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 19.8.</note> when he carrieth this minde.</p>
               <p>The fourth thing to bee conſidered in this iuſt man, is his profunditie in the practiſe of righteouſneſſe, which will not ſuffer him to damnifie his neighbour, nor to vſe any nimble ſhifts, whereby to increaſe his eſtate; but to build all his fortunes (as men vſually ſpeake) vpon honeſt and plaine dealing. And hence is that ſaying, A good and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23814:8"/>iuſt man wil neither <hi>damno afficere quenquam, nec aliquid dolo annectere rei ſuae,</hi> tricks and ſhifts are odious to a righteous man, yea though he might gaine Kingdoms therby. Such a one was iuſt <hi>Iob,</hi> whoſe greatneſſe was a veile to protect the poore, and no priuiledge to ſet him on worke to prey vpon the diſtreſſed and needy, as in our dayes it is (too common) wherein, alaſſe, many make themſelues great by vſing trickes and ſhifts: and ſome vſe their greatneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their poore neighbours, as a meanes to maintaine their owne prodigall and ſinfull courſes, or to make rich their lewd poſteritie, who ſpend all amongſt harlots and varlets, which themſelues haue wretchedly gotten by kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping backe the labourers wages, skinning of the poore, and grinding the face of the needie; a ſinne that in theſe daies and in this countrey crieth for vengeance. But I ſpeake of a iuſt man, who is farre from this behauiour; and the liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſentation whereof we may ſee in theſe particulars: that he vnderſtandeth the wayes of equitie, that he liueth not as borne to himſelfe, but for the good of others, that he is content with that he hath, and laſtly, that neither with <hi>Abſolons</hi> lying flatterie, nor with <hi>Geheſies</hi> couetous bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, nor with <hi>Achitophels</hi> ſubtile policie, nor with the Lyon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like might and power he will adde one cubite vnto his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but ſtill keeping an vpright heart inward, and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe within the confines of righteouſnes outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he paſſeth on in this world vntil he come to the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted period of his life; and marke him then, for <hi>finis illius pax,</hi> his end is peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>His end is Peace.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> doth not ſay his life is in peace, but his end; for, for the moſt part the beſt men beare the heauieſt croſſes, and are troubled with moſt oppoſitions, beeing in this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23814:8"/>world like a Lilley amongſt the Thornes, and haue their dwelling where Satans thrones are ſet vp: and this is their portion, which notwithſtanding they patiently vndergoe that they may finiſh their courſe with ioy.</p>
               <p>The Hebrews vnderſtand by this word Peace, al hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe; the Grecians a ſetled quietneſſe of the ſoule, in which, as in a ſure harbour, it reſteth in much ioy and true content: agreeing to which is that of <hi>S. Auguſtine, Pax est ſerenitas mentis, tranquillitas animi,</hi> and this peace is either with God, whom we neuer ſaw, and yet loue him and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in him; or peace of conſcience; or peace with men: the firſt is from the aſſurance of our
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.</note> iuſtification by Chriſt Ieſus: the ſecond is grounded vpon the former; for from the knowledge that <hi>Dauid</hi> is at one with God, is <hi>Dauids</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>in pace accubabo pariter &amp; dormiam,</hi> I will lie downe in peace and reſt, becauſe thou Lord art my ſafe-guard: the laſt is from both the former; for who ſo is at one with God and himſelfe, will ſeeke peace and enſue it, as
<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> did with <hi>Lot.</hi> The firſt, which is peace with God, giueth a man boldneſſe to come to the Throne of grace, with an aſſured
<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16.</note> confidence to find fauour in the needfull time of trouble. The ſecond is the braſen wall of mans defence, within which there is a
<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.8.</note> continuall feaſt and domeſticall ioy. The third is ſo good a bleſsing, that, as <hi>Caſſ.</hi> ſpeakes, it is <hi>imago angelicae conuerſationis,</hi> the liuely image of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall behauior. But me thinks I heare ſome man ſaying vnto me, That it's impoſsible a good man ſhould bee at peace with the vngodly; for what peace, ſo long as the witchcrafts and whoredome of <hi>Ieſabell</hi> remaine in great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance?</p>
               <p>I anſwer; <hi>Pax est concordiam habere cum moribus probis, litigare cum vitijs,</hi> true peace is to be at one with mens good
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23814:9"/>behauiour; but alwayes to ſtand out at the ſwords point againſt all ſinfull and wicked attempts: and therfore when we ſee the iuſt and vpright to be at odds with the workers of iniquitie, it is not in any diſlike of their perſons, but of their conditions. And out of all this appeareth a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt the ſonnes of God, and the children of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial;</hi> for to the former there is a true quietnes of mind, but to the latter no
<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.21.</note> peace. For either they vnderſtand not their owne miſerie, and ſo ſeeke not for Gods mercie, the feeling whereof bringeth true peace; or elſe they ſee their faults ſo fearefull that they flie in deſpaire from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God (as <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> did) and ſo haue nothing but vnſpeakeable diſquietneſſe and horrors in their ſoules. And laſtly for peace with men: they thinke all men hate them,
<note place="margin">Timuerunt ibi vbi non timor.</note> when, God knoweth, they are hunted and purſued by their owne hearts, which will not let them be at quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with others, becauſe they are at continuall iarring with themſelues; and therefore euen vpon ſuſpicion (they know not of what) they grow falſe and treacherous to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey deale withall.</p>
               <p>The concluſion then is, That true peace, eyther with men, or with our ſelues, and with God, is not in nor with wicked men; and on the contrary ſide, Marke the iuſt, and conſider the vpright man, for his end is peace. Thus much ſhall be ſufficient for the meaning of the wordes of my Text. Now giue me leaue in a few words to point at ſuch inſtructions as naturally ariſe out of them.</p>
               <p>The firſt propoſition is, That the wayes of a Chriſtian are obvious to the view of men, and his actions are ſuch as may be ſcanned and marked, and are not confined within the cloyſters of obſcuritie; but like a light ſet vpon a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtick that ſhineth to all that are in the houſe: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23814:9"/>we are bidden to marke both the perfection and the righteouſneſſe of a good man. I know one point of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity is contemplation; but that wanteth life when pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe doth not follow: and therfore it's no ill conceit of him that called a holy man <hi>Mary Martha.</hi> For as S. <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſpeaketh of Loue, that the touch-ſtone thereof is in the works of charitie: ſo
<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.</note> may I ſay with S. <hi>Iames</hi> of true faith in whomſoeuer it is, that it ought to be ſhewed, and is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated by the fruits thereof. Shall I ſay that a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is a good Paſtor, which nothing reſembleth his Maſter the great Biſhop and ſheepheard of our ſoules, in feeding and helping the diſtreſſed? And can we think a Magiſtrate to be a good Ruler, when in the execution of his office no man can ſee, <hi>obſerua &amp; vide,</hi> either for puniſhing of ſinne, or aduancing of vertue? but rather behold and ſee how he boulſtereth vp, or ſlily paſſeth ouer all impious and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous profaneneſſe. And doe you hold them a good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which make no conſcience to ſhew the vertues of Chriſt whom they profeſſe? <hi>No, no.</hi> By their fruits you ſhall know them, is an Euangelicall rule. And marke and behold; for where vertue is, it may be felt, heard, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</p>
               <p>The ſecond propoſition which generally ariſeth from theſe words, is, That we may not giue doome of any till his actions be duly conſidered: for they are Herralds, to proclaime who, and what he is. A good man is not to be condemned, becauſe a crue of ſinfull wretches that looke through the mirrour of their miſ-informed mindes, crie out <hi>crucifige:</hi> neither is any ill man good, becauſe the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſinfull drunken wretches prefer him before Chriſt: then <hi>obſerua &amp; vide,</hi> will bee a good ground whereon to build our determinations, and then ſhall we iudge righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:23814:10"/>iudgement, and neyther ſuffer our ſelues to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled with ſupercillious lookes, nor condemne the iuſt whoſe end is peace.</p>
               <p>The laſt point I entreat you obſerue in the obſeruation of my Text, is, That a good life is graced and bleſſed with a happy death.
<note place="margin">Auguſt. de do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina chriſtiana, non male mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur qui bene vixerit &amp; vix bene moritur qui male.</note> We haue only one example of a man that liued ill and died well, and yet his repentance is ſet down with the fruits thereof (as ſhort time as he had): but wee haue no example of any man that liued well, and died ill; which <hi>Balaam</hi> did vnderſtand, when hee wiſhed to die the death of the righteous. Of theſe Baalamites there be no few, who dedicate their liues to vanity, and yet forſooth (if wiſhing would preuaile) they would haue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for their inheritance. But bee not deceiued, my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, for ſince they ſow in the fleſh they ſhall therof reape corruption; and who ſo ſoweth in the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpirit reape life euerlaſting. Labour therefore my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to ſpend the ſhort time of your life which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, in the truth of holineſſe, without hypocriſie; in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe without ſinfull vncleaneneſſe: ſo ſhall your end be peace in your ſelues, peace with men, and peace with God, which paſſeth all vnderſtanding. And thus you ſee the whole of a Chriſtian man, both in the premiſſes and concluſion; the premiſſes two, perfection and iuſtice: the concluſion well ſuting both <hi>Maior &amp; Minor, finis illius pax.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Demonſtration of which truth, giue me leaue to ſet before you in the life and death of that honorable Knight and Baronet: for the ſolemnizing of whoſe direfull obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, we are at this time met together; of whoſe life and death if I ſhould ſay nothing, I might iuſtly bee accuſed of vnthankfulneſſe to God for paſsing by ſuch excellent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, as I know the Diuine Maieſtie had bewtified him
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23814:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>withall. And if I ſhall ſay much, I feare the ordinary aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of flattery, which blacke-mouthed enuie ſpitteth out to diſgrace vertue withall, may perhaps be caſt vpon mee: and therefore to auoide <hi>Silla</hi> on the one hand, and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribdis</hi> on the other, I will ſpeake nothing but that I dare auouch for truth before the Angels in heauen, and which many in this place can witneſſe of their owne knowledge, before men vpon earth. My regard of this honourable Knight while he liued was not mercinarie, and my report of him at this time is not in hope of reward: and therefore without any further Preface, thus much in the Front of my ſpeech I may ſay, That he was a Gentleman of as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and honourable continuance as any in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and therfore not to be blamed that he was deſirous (being reſolued that in law and conſcience it was equall (as himſelfe confeſſed he was) to vphold the honour of his houſe in his name, which for nine deſcents hath continued at this his houſe at <hi>Snarford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This truely-honoured Knight and Baronet, if you pleaſe, may be remembred in the gifts of nature, of art, of grace, or in the practiſe of them all. In the firſt, he was for perſon and naturall endowments very complete; and by the ſecond the former were ſo well diſpoſed, that in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, Adamant-like he drew the hearts of many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to affect: and to ſpeake plainly, the eyes of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in this Countrey was ſet vpon him, as vpon a worthy obiect in his place and calling. In the gifts of grace, this may I report; that he knew the truth:
<note place="margin">We were euer graced by him, and in whoſe company hee tooke great content.</note> ſo doe many wicked men. He loued the truth, and the inſtruments that publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the ſame: ſo doe none but the good. He was coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious for the truth: and ſo are none but Gods ſecret ones; and from his knowledge the ground of his faith, and from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23814:11"/>his loue the fruit of his beleefe, and from his courage the pledge of his ſanctitie; he had the ground of <hi>S. Pauls</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioicing, which is a good conſcience.</p>
               <p>For the practiſe of all theſe graces, let mee intreat you conſider him as a husband to a wife, a Maſter of a family, a friend to his acquaintance, a Magiſtrate in his country, and a Chriſtian in all.</p>
               <p>For the firſt: hee dwelled with his wife as a man of knowledge, free from inhumane auſteritie on the one ſide, and voyde of fond and idle complementing indulgence on the other; which wiſe and Chriſtian behauiour, was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by his vertuous Ladie.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond, as he was a Maſter of a Family: whileſt he was a father (though God knoweth) that was but for a ſhort time; he vſed that bleſſing as though hee had not poſſeſſed it. And as he was a Maſter ouer ſeruants, this was his care; that all vnder his charge were bountifully rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for their ſeruice, and wanted no means (though to his great charge) to know God. Such as were vertuous wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no encouragement: ſuch as were leſſe tractable to goodneſſe, in the ſpirit of mildenſſe he vſed all good means to reclaime them. In briefe, he was to his ſeruants a father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Maſter, in authoritie, in care, in counſell, in countenance, in loue, and in bountie; I ſay in bounty to them whilſt he liued, and in his large portions he hath cut out of his eſtate for them after his death: ſo that if any that followed him be irregular like <hi>Geheſie,</hi> annointing his fingers with bribes, or ryoting with the euill ſeruant in the Goſpel; I ſay no more but this, They haue not ſo learned Chriſt, neither by precept, nor by their Maſters practiſe.</p>
               <p>For the third point, as he was a friend: let enquirie be made when euer he failed any that had occaſion to vſe his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23814:11"/>helpe; and for true affection, hee was, as often he ſaid of a friend <hi>(alter idem)</hi> or as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh, one that loueth at all times: rather with <hi>Mordach</hi> enquiring how his friends did, and in what caſe they ſtood, then ſtaying till hee was ſought vnto for his helpe; and more reioycing to do good to thoſe he loued, in caſe they wanted his help, then faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vpon ſuch as were happed with the thicke clay of worldly proſperitie. He was a right and true-hearted <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> and ſuch a friend may I ſay he was, as I feare I ſhall neuer finde till my ſoule reſt with his.</p>
               <p>For the fourth point, which concerneth him as he was a Magiſtrate: If <hi>Iethro</hi> were liuing hee would haue called for him, as one fit to aſſiſt <hi>Moſes.</hi> Hee wanted no courage for a good cauſe, and to out-face and reſiſt the wicked at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts and practiſes of vniuſt and vnlawfull diſorders: his feare of God and ſoundneſſe in Religion, was neuer queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable: his vpright dealing voyde of partialitie or perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſpect, may be witneſſed in that generall lamentation taken vp for him by the people in this Country: and for his hating of couetouſneſſe, and eſpecially in the executing of his office, his name ſhall not die whileſt any that knew him is left aliue. Who euer knew that he made vſe of the countries mony, or was vnwilling to come to any account for collected money, committed to his charge for the countries behoofe? hee was a man very much employed with the right honourable the Lord <hi>Willoughbie,</hi> as Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Lieutenant vnder that moſt worthy Lord Threaſorer, and moſt wiſe Counſeller, the Lord <hi>Burley.</hi> And when in the dayes of our late renowned and neuer to be forgotten Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (the mirrour of Chriſtendome) there was great employment for men and money, to keepe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſuperſtitious and rebellious Iriſh, beſides the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:23814:12"/>paines he tooke, and the great coſt he was at to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſeruice; he disburſed payments out of his owne purſe for the country, till Seſſments could be conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made, and the money collected. And this can all you his fellow-labourers witneſſe, that neither feare nor fauor, affinity nor conſanguinity, did euer hinder him from going on in an vpright courſe to doe ſeruice to God, and our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious King. Neyther was he voyde of compaſſion in the execution of Iuſtice: No, no, when hee dealt with Papiſts, or had to puniſh hard-hearted Atheiſts (which ſome refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to meddle withall) this was his rule, that he would <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidare peccatum,</hi> but <hi>ſaluare hominem:</hi> yea ſuch was his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, that I know ſom Recuſants that could not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by arguments (for vſually reaſon cannot preuaile with them) were moued and won to come to the Church by his milde, mercifull, and louing perſwaſion that he vſed vnto them; and ſuch as he could not reclaim, he did great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bemone and pitty. In the caſe of <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> this was his rule; <hi>qui iudicat parte inaudita altera, aequum licet ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, haud aequus iudex.</hi> In briefe, thus did hee ſpend thirtie yeares of that his life, which was in the whole but one and fiftie; neuer refuſing any paines or endeauours, though to the ſpending of his eſtate, the weakening (yea, as many here know, and eſpecially my ſelfe) to the wearying of his body and the empayring of his health. And let mee not forget, that the laſt iourney that he tooke was for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, the ſafetie and peace of the King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; wherein his behauior was ſo commendable, and his ſpeeches ſo good, as were it not that theſe my lines would ſwell vnto too great a quantity, I would ſet them down as his Swan-like ſong within few dayes before his death. But to leaue theſe things, the laſt conſideration is of his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:23814:12"/>behauior, which was eyther more publike; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in obſerue his humilitie, his charitable mercifulneſſe: or more priuate, as his vnſeene deuotion and charitie. For the firſt, I may truely ſay of him, That hee made himſelfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to thoſe of low degree, euer abhorring himſelfe with <hi>Iob</hi> (in the ſeruice of God) in the aſhes of true humilitie; an argument of a ſanctified heart, and of a mind fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue further grace from God.</p>
               <p>For his mercifulnes, enquire after that amongſt his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants: and if they ſpeake truely, they will confeſſe that they haue beene vſed ſo, as few of their neighbours were dealt withall. Who euer knew him take the forfeiture of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Leaſe, or when fines and rents were vnpaide at times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon, to vſe any extremitie to get the ſame? Nay, what Tenant euer deſired forbearance for a time, eyther of Rent or Fine, that had to his demaund a deniall? The deſolate Widdowes and Fatherleſſe-Orphanes, that liued vnder him, were both regarded and prouided for by him. Secondly, inquire of his hoſpitality, not only to the better ſort of people, but eſpecially to the poore; and you ſhall heare that their ſoules did bleſſe him whileſt he liued, and are now ſorrowfull for his death. Indeed this I confeſſe, that in his hoſpitalitie he iudged drinking-banquets fitter for profane <hi>Baltaſar</hi> with his companions, then to be vſed in Chriſtian meetings. Thirdly, if you liſt to heare more of his mercifulnes, I doubt not but many haue taſted of it, in his daily lending of money without pawnes or pledges, or euer taking intereſt, or forfeiture of bond (the crying ſinnes of this age.) If any vnknowne to him haue made vſe of this his mercifulneſſe, like brodging Brokers, I ſay to ſuch a one as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Simon Magus;</hi> for ſure I am that hee was free in lending to all ſorts of people, both in this Countrey
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:23814:13"/>and ſome other parts within this Kingdome, <hi>Carendo poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us quam fruendo:</hi> His vertue in this kinde both to Clergie and Laitie will appeare after his death. But I am yet in the Suburbes of his mercifull dealing. Now let meenter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the walls therof; and the firſt thing that preſents it ſelfe vnto my view is his liberality to poore Schollers &amp; places of learning: and herein I might name vnto you ſixe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and profitable Preachers, which were brought vp in the Vniuerſities at his coſt and charges. Some now at this time in thoſe places taſte of his bountie, and many both in Church and Common-wealth, towards their education haue receiued exhibition from him till they were fitter for better fortunes. But to leaue perſons, and to come to pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Magdalen</hi> Colledge in Cambridge, the famous Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Oxford, and <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> Colledge in the ſame V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſity, where hee was ſeaſoned with the grounds of learning by the now reuerend Preſident of that houſe,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Doct. <hi>Spencer.</hi>
                  </note> whom he deerly loued; can tell you that hee was a good benefactor to thoſe places in his life time: and I muſt tell you that he hath giuen a large quantity of inheritance by yeare for euer vnto <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> Colledge in Oxford. I need not relate vnto you how he hath endowed the free-Schoole in Market Raiſon, with an yearely penſion to maintaine a Schoole-maſter: and that hee hath giuen an yearly maintenance for the planting of a Preacher at Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton one of his neighbour Townes, where I heare by the Pariſhioners there was neuer ſetled Preacher in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of any man, nor ſcarce twenty Sermons this twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares, except by his meanes; and yet the Pariſh is great, and the law of our Church, thankes be to God, hath commanded otherwiſe. Neither may I let paſſe, ſince I am naming theſe things, what great care he had to further
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:23814:13"/>Religion, how free hee was in beſtowing thoſe ſpirituall preferments that were in his gift, looking at nothing but how to prouide for the good of Gods people; farre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from the practiſe of many Patrons, that let nothing paſſe without What wilt thou giue me? But he was ſo free from this ſinne, that I haue heard him often earneſtly wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, that a lawe might bee made by which the Patron ſhould be ſworne of his free gift, as well as the preſented of his free entrance, without any contract eyther directly or indirectly. Shall I goe on to tell you of other deeds of mercie? how for theſe thirtie yeares hee gaue tenne olde and poore men gownes and money euery yeare, and of late added twentie more to the number: how Market Raiſon had foure pounds yearely towards the releefe of their poore, beſides a hundreth and ſixtie pound that was giuen to helpe the poorer and yonger ſort of tradſemen by good ſummes, to paſſe from one to another as there was need; and now by his Will hath giuen a great ſumme of money to build an Hoſpitall, and a large yearly penſion for euer to relieue ſuch as ſhall be placed in it: beſides the relieuing of tenne poore men with a certaine penſion, and gownes for euer, that ſhall be choſen out of the Townes neere adioyning to his houſe at <hi>Snarford.</hi> In briefe, of late he hath beene at extraordinary charge to build, finiſh, and furniſh a houſe fitting his place and calling: and I haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued that ſince the laying of the firſt ſtone of that houſe, which is ſeuen yeares paſt, his charity hath encreaſed in his large ſummes he gaue to the poore in this Countrey, as though hee meant to make ſure the foundation of his houſe with the workes of charitie, or haſted to prouide a Manſion for his ſoule in heauen, before his earthly houſe was finiſhed. Now for his priuate bountie to poore Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:23814:14"/>and others, of which he now findeth the comfort; as it was knowne to none better then my ſelfe. Onely this I wil ſay according to <hi>Salomons</hi> direction, He caſt his bread vpon the waters; and as our Sauiour ſaith, his right knew not what his left hand did: for many a poore Scholler that neuer ſaw his face, hath taſted of his loue; whoſe prayers to God for him, though vnknowne, like harbingers haue entred into heauen, to take vp roome for his comfort in the ſauing grace of God. Now for his priuat deuotion, beſides his daily reading in the booke of God, and his paines hee tooke in other bookes, eſpecially in the writings of Biſhop <hi>Iewel,</hi> which hee greatly eſteemed, hauing found ſingular good out of them, as vpon the day of his death he did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge: This one thing I cannot omit, that euery Munday in the morning he did in his priuate ſtudie recall to mind what he had learned vpon the Sabbath day, and what vſe he was to make to himſelf of the ſame. And then his manner was to pray, That all the weeke and the whole time of his life after hee might ſhew the fruit of that his learning, and ſo he addreſſed himſelfe to the works of his calling: a cuſtom worth imitation by all you Gentlemen, and all other Chriſtians that meane to attaine the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he now enioyeth. If any ſhall aske me, how I knew theſe things: I anſwer, not by the ſounding of a Trumpet, or the ringing of a Bell, when he went about theſe priuate duties of pietie; but by a priuat conference I had with him of late: in which, as he asked counſell touching ſom need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full queſtions that concerned his comfort, ſo he did open himſelfe in this matter to me, not with a deſire it ſhould be knowne, but in humility to be further directed, as in other points which I will not name, ſo in this one, Whether it were lawfull in his priuate prayers, wherein he was to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:23814:14"/>and confeſſe the ſecrets of his hart to the Almighty, to kneele vpon a Cuſhion? by which queſtion in what a baſe account of himſelfe he appeared before God, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to all that ſhall well conſider thereof. And withall it doeth much condemne the proud behauiour of many, which in publique and priuate praiers diſpoſe themſelues as though they did conteſt with God, and ſtood not ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and crying for mercie and pardon for their treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous rebellions againſt the Almightie; but with the proud Phariſee, were bragging of their deeds. And thus he ſpent his life; in which he was an inſtrument of much good, a faithfull friend to the well-diſpoſed, a mercifull Iudge of offenders, and a worthy example of vertue where euer hee came. Now for the time of his ſickeneſſe and death.</p>
               <p>His ſickeneſſe was ſeuen dayes: in all which time, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit his pains were often extreame, yet neuer was he heard to vtter any impatient ſpeech. Little or nothing did hee ſleepe eyther day or night: and yet this was Gods mercie to him, that hee neuer vttered any offenſiue word, that might argue eyther leuitie or impietie. For the moſt part of fiue dayes and nights I was with him,
<note place="margin">Whoſe calling was much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored by him in all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedinges, and to the meaneſt of whome he was a worthie Patron aganſt all oppoſitions</note> and ſo were many of his good friends, &amp; diuers reuerend Miniſters, in whoſe godly ſpeeches, and deuout prayers, and good companie he much reioyced, and did acknowledge Gods goodneſſe, that thoſe he loued in his life, ſhould be with him at his death. I confeſſe he was diuers times and wayes aſſaulted by the Tempter, who vſually came and iniected temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into him when he ſhould haue taken his naturall reſt: againſt all which hee made reſiſtance by the Word of truth. And acquainting me with the particulars that were laid to his charge, when I ſhewed him what ſpirituall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor he might vſe to quench thoſe fierie darts, hee would
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:23814:15"/>pauſe for a time, as meditating of what I had ſaid; in the end hee did ſtill breake out into theſe wordes: Lord Ieſu ſtrengthen my faith, and Lord I beleeue, helpe my vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe. He was much in meditation, often in priuat mentall prayer, and often he did tell me, that thinking of death he did find no feare of it, as formerly in his fleſh he had done. Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Wedneſday in the morning I perceiuing his ſtrength to decay, and his paines to encreaſe, entreated him that he would ſet his houſe in order, and determine of his worldly affaires; and he looking cheerefully vpon me, thus ſpake: Now I know you loue mee, as I am ſure you haue done long, in that you wiſh I might die in peace, which (ſaid he) I aſſure my ſelfe I ſhall doe: and for my worldly eſtate, I haue made my Will, I haue diſpoſed of my land, though not as you haue often wiſhed, yet ſo as I hope it ſhal ſtand, and I will impart the ſame vnto my brother <hi>Wray,</hi> which ſhortly after he did. All that day he was in great paines, often deſiring me to pray for him, and ſometimes greeuing that his bodily paines would not giue him leaue to make a vocall prayer; yet once vpon a ſudden with lifted-vp eyes and handes, hee powered out his heart in ſuch a heauenly manner as might aſſure the hearers that Gods ſpirit ſpake in him. Vpon Wedneſday in the night about ten of the clocke he fell into a ſlumber, in which he continued but a while, and, as he ſaid when he awaked, all my bodily pains are gone away, but my mind is much troubled with cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſome thoughts; againſt which he made reſiſtance by priuat prayer, and by conference with one of his ſeruants that attended him. About two of the clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning I came to him, and he told me what combats he had with his enemie: and I giuing him ſuch counſell againſt the ſame as God gaue me wiſdom to do; he receiued it ſo hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:23814:15"/>as I was much comforted with it. Preſently he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red we might pray together, that, ſaid he, I may haue a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling comfort of that you haue ſpoken; which we did, and at the end of praier hee concluded with repeating this word thrice, Amen. Immediatly after he made an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent confeſſion of his faith, and of the hope that was in him touching his ſaluation; concluding that his confeſſion with a praier, that God would ſtrengthen him in that faith vnto the end and in his end. After the end of which pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er he lifted vp his eyes and hands to heauen, and vttered theſe words: Now is my comforter come, and hell gates ſhall not preuaile againſt mee, and by the power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of thy ſpirit I know I ſhall finiſh my courſe with ioy, and after receiue the crowne of life: from the end of which prayer and confeſſion hee was neuer troubled with any temptation. Then he being quiet for ſome halfe houre, I asked him, whether hee could call to mind that euer hee dealt hardly with any man, and if he had ſo done to make reſtitution? he ſmilingly anſwered, I thanke God I neuer tooke nor got any goods vnlawfully, or vncharitably, and I thanke you for putting me in mind of this point. Once more he made a confeſſion of his faith, vttered his diſlike of Popery, profeſsing that he had often ſtudied to ſee if he could find any comfort out of the Popiſh doctrine; and confeſſed he could not ſee any thing in the Popiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion but ambition, humane policie, and Heatheniſh ſuperſtition. He often made his prayers to God by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and with others: he gaue moſt heauenly counſaile to his friends, and to his ſeruants; and where he thought the loue of the world had taken too deepe hold in any, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded from the ſame: verifying that truth, That he that is conuerted himſelfe will ſtrengthen others. The ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:23814:16"/>that he vttered that day were many, and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable: amongſt which I noted theſe which follow. O my ſoule truſt ſtill in God, for he is thy rocke and defence; I find it is good to hold me faſt by my God. O Lord I haue none in heauen nor earth beſides thee, and therefore onely into thy hands I commend my ſoule, for thou art my God and my redeemer. O God thou haſt kept mee from the wombe vntill now, forſake me not, but let my ſoule, my tongue, and all that is within me praiſe thy holy name. As the Hart breatheth after the water brookes, ſo my ſoule thirſteth after thee, O Lord, in this barren and drie land (and clapping his hands vpon his heart, he ſpake further) here where no water of comfort is, but that thou haſt powred into it onely through thy ſonne Chriſt; and therefore to thee be honour &amp; praiſe for euermore. Thus he continued and ſpent his time, to the great comfort of al beholders, vntill his ſenſes externall decayed; which hee perceiued ſo ſenſibly, that he did tell when the parts of his body did die, as, when his legge, his right eye, his right hand, and other parts were dead: hee would ſay, now is ſuch a part dead. The vſe of his tongue God gaue him till within half an houre before his laſt breath, with which he vttered many holy ſpeeches, wherof theſe were the laſt: Forſake me not, O Lord, Be not thou farre from me, O my God, Haſt thee to help me, O my Lord my ſaluation; And now Lord what wait I for? My hope is onely in thee, and into thy hands I commend my ſpirit; Lord Ieſus receiue my ſoule: and alwayes hee concluded his prayers which himſelfe vttered, or which were made by others, with theſe words, To whom be praiſe and glorie for euermore. Yea, when his ſpeech failed wee might perceiue him to pray, though he could not vtter perfect words, and ſo to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:23814:16"/>continue, concluding his prayer with the ſame thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, till hee pronounced this word Amen in this ſort; A me me en, as though his ſoule, before it went out of his bodie, had beene keeping a part in that heauenly <hi>Anthem</hi> with the foure and twentie Elders, which ſing to him that ſitteth vpon the Throne, and liueth for euermore. And thus hee continued, till with much comfort and peace his life ended, and his ſoule entred into the Kingdome of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (which now I aſſure my ſelfe he doth enioy, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the God of heauen bring all his Saints in his appointed time) which was about foure of the clocke in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, vpon the eight and twentieth of October, when he had liued one and fiftie yeares, ſeuen daies, and ſome odde houres: too ſhort a time, if it had pleaſed God otherwiſe. What can the remouing of him out of the houſe of clay propheſie, but that God threatneth ſome puniſhment vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs the ſuruiuors, when ſo worthy, ſo wiſe, ſo vertuous, ſo religious, and noble a Gentleman in the ſtrength of his manhood is taken away? of whoſe life and death I haue ſpoken the more largely, firſt, to let the Papiſts ſee that we preach not, nor our good hearers practiſe not fleſhly liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as they falſly accuſe vs: ſecondly, to let you Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Iuſtices know what an example of vertue and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe you haue loſt. For though I doubt not but there be many good ones left yet, I am ſure you will all confeſſe he was the Bell-Wether in the flocke: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I would haue him whom this worthy Knight hath appointed and adopted to ſucceede in his houſe, and the greateſt part of his eſtate, to imitate him in the courſe of his life, to whome hee is ſo much beholding for the loue of his name, which hath cauſed him to caſt ſuch extraordinarie fortunes vpon him, leſt perhappes it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:23814:17"/>be ſaid, <hi>O domus antiqua quam diſpari iam dominaris domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> or leſt he heare <hi>Non domus Domino, ſed Dominus domo:</hi> Fourthly, let it not be wondred that ſeruants which haue loſt ſo worthy a Maſter; and Countrey which haſt loſt ſo good a Gouernour; doe take vp a great lamentation. And for his worthy Ladie, who <hi>Rachel</hi>-like will not be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; doe not condemne her: for the conſideration of the comfort ſhee is depriued of, amongſt the wiſe that did know her happineſſe in the enioying of ſuch a husband, will in ſome ſort make her excuſe, and worke pittie and compaſsion for her ſorrow. Howbeit withall I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, I know none that hath more cauſe of comfort, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that aſſurance ſhe may haue of a husbands happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe then ſhee. Laſtly, for my ſelfe; if mournfull teares, or aſtoniſhing thoughts could recall him back againe from the graue, I would thinke my ſelfe bound, for the loſſe of ſo worthy a friend, to wiſh that my head were a fountain of teares, to lament day and night for the fall of ſo good a man in Iſrael. But I haue not ſo learned Chriſt; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thus much onely will I ſay: Remember his life as an example worth imitation; Remember his death: by the ſight whereof I do confeſſe I was better inſtructed how to die then by all the precepts that euer I read of that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And ſo marke his life, for it was good and holy; and his end, for it was peace. And ſo in peace, I leaue him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying an eternall ſurpaſſing weight of glory; aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my ſelfe withall, that vpon earth <hi>ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per honos, nomen<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuum, laudeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, manebunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:23814:17"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
